John Gordon Last updated August 11, 2022

john.gordon@gordonjl.com • 207.329.4111 • www.linkedin.com/in/gordonjl/86 Edwards Street • Portland, Maine • USA

Summary

Experienced software engineering manager, with hard and soft skills.

Moving to San Francisco in the '90s during the dotcom boom, I became a coder on a 40-developer, remotelydistributed team, developing large features for a major

retail banking website. After becoming a skilled tech lead, I moved into management in 2013, combining my communication skills with my technical abilities to grow my own team of software developers from eight to eighteen members.

Experience

Portland Webworks

Portland, Maine 2013 – 2021

Director of Software Development

Portland Webworks is a software consulting company, specialized in creating web-based, data-driven applications. I report directly to the company owner. In charge of a team of 18 developers, I am responsible for managing the team, introducing and maintaining project process, supporting the Business Development unit as technical consultant, and coordinating with clients and other departments within the company.

- Grew the software development team from 8 to 18 developers, member tenure averaging 4 years.
- Replaced Waterfall process with Scrum and Kanban methodologies.
- Advanced the team's careers, assigning members to developer and techincal lead roles, and providing feedback in 1:1 sessions.
- Increased accountability by gathering team and company metrics and displaying on monitors in the office.
- Freed up resources and kept team morale high by personally maintaining legacy projects (JSF, Struts, ExtJS, DB2).
- Coordinated applying Enterprise best practices across four scrum teams working on two large, multi-year projects.
- Increased team productivity by standardizing processes and tools across projects, reducing ramp-up time for new team members.
- Introduced hiring remote developers, now a third of the team, making it possible to staff our increasing number of projects.
- Oversee operations for typically four to five simultaneously running projects

Senior Software Developer

2010 - 2013

Technical lead on projects key to the company's success

- Developed a custom word processor tool that tightly integrated with Maine's Judicial systems, allowing for auto-insertion of court case information into legal documents.
- Perform B/A and project technical Discovery, formed teams, and gave direction with both in-house and remote European-based teams.
- Created a Single Page Application, with offline capabilities, to track fisherman's seafood catch
- Developed online Medicaid renewal application system for Idaho's Departement of Health and Welfare
- Led the adoption of Google Apps and Bitbucket

Technologies

Java • Spring and Spring Boot • Hibernate • AngularJS 1.x • Angular 2+ • Cocoa • ReactJS • Objective-C • Oracle • MySql • Postgresql • ExtJS • Clover ETL • Groovy • Grails • Ruby on Rails • Selenium

Technical Lead

IDEXX

Westbrook, Maine

Feb 2009 – March 2010

IDEXX is an American multinational corporation engaged in the development, manufacture, and distribution of products and services for the companion animal veterinary, livestock and poultry, water testing, and dairy markets. I lead the development of a Laboratory Information Management System. The team included five developers, two QA, and other support staff. After one year of development, the project was delivered on time and deployed to all of IDEXX's global laboratories. The system handled every facet of laboratory activity, from requisition and sample intake processing, testing (both via manual entry and insturment interface), analysis, reporting, and billing. The application is based

on SOA architecture, utilizing Oracle's Service Bus, Weblogic Integration platform, and Data Services Integration backend.

- Worked closely with the project manager and business analyst team to identify work load for all sprints, delegating work to individual developers.
- Actively develop web services and Swing code in addition to leading the team.
- Responsible for change control, branching, and merging of the code base.
- Created automated, one-click, build-and-deployment process for publishing Webstart Swing client application to the various environments.
- introduced Atlassian Fisheye/Crucible, Hudson and Jabber Chatroom to the department, all geared towards improving the continuous integration feedback loop.
- General management tasks for direct reports; performance reviews, one-to-ones. Led daily status meeting; 15 attendees.

Technologies

Maven, Spring AOP • XDoclet • Oracle ODSI • Oracel OSB • Ora- cle WLI • Axis Web services • Watir • nUnit • jUnit • jMock • Ant • NAnt • UML, Weblogic 10/11g • Java Swing • Javascript

Washington Mutual Bank (WAMU)

Emeryville, California

Senior Software Developer

2002 - 2007

Washington Mutual Bank was the largest US savings and loan. I worked on many projects, but my most significant work was developing and maintaining the mortgage product-pricing web service and working on an Agile team tasked with developing new industry functionality that for the first time enabled customers to open bank accounts totally online. I gained invaluable experience working on a remotely-distributed team of forty developers, seeing how a large application is developed, maintained, and deployed.

- Enabled funding of new online account originations via debit/credit card.
- Implemented one-step account origination form for eligible customers. Form wrapped existing wizard-based application process to present a single form for users to complete.
- Completed a major refactoring of Wamu's account originations funding process.
- Modularized each funding option to enable easy addition of future funding options.
- Implemented automated build process for wamu.com, dramatically cutting down build time and greatly increasing overall stability of the code base.
- Designed and implemented back end processes for online overdraft notification to process high traffic levels.
- Created J2ee Axis Web Service to wrap legacy systems for use in modern, front-end application, decoupling the web app from legacy system and greatly speeding development.
- Created ASP.Net longbeachmortgage.com broker web site to display loan pro-cessing status. Site implemented using Web Service SOA strategy.
- Created and maintained a high-traffic .Net Web Service and accompanying man- agement/testing J2ee web application, responsible for providing mortgage pricing data for multiple applications.
- Created internal incentives and promotions ASP.Net web application for sales
- team. Heavy emphasis on de-coupling the view enabled quarterly re-design of the site without changes to the underlying business logic.

Technologies

C# • Visual Basic • VBScript • Javascript • XML • XSLT • WSDL ASP.Net • Java Servlets • XDoclet • nUnit • NAnt • UML • MS Visual Studio 2003/2005 • Mingle • Crucible/Fisheye • MS Sql Server • CVS • Subversion • Perforce • MS Visio • MSI Installer • Microsoft.Net • Web Services

Skills

Technical expertise: Software design and implementation, with(in) a team. deep knowledge of Agile methodologies (Scrum and Kanban), continuous integration (Jenkins and Bitbucket Pipelines). Solid knowledge of web technologies: HTML+CSS, XML, REST, SOAP and JavaScript (Angular and ReactJS). Linux administration skills: Bash, MySQL, DB2, PostgresSQL, virtualization/cloud (Docker). ETL, proposal development.

Education

Montgomery Community College Associates Degree

Rockville, Maryland 1991 – 1993

Interests

Non-exhaustive and in alphabetical order: alternative transportation, chess, parenting, poker, software engineering (methodologies), squash, travel